[SPEAKER_00]: So, yes, the sutta for today, it's Saṃyutta Nikāya 35, 246.
[SPEAKER_00]: Probably most people would have read it.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's like a famous dissimilar of the lute.
[SPEAKER_00]: But it's really the things that are mentioned in the suttas before the dissimilar of the lute that are kind of more interesting, well, certainly more relevant for the practice.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because whatever bhikkhu or a bhikkhuni, regarding forms cognizable by the eye, should there arise desire, or greed, or hate, or delusion, or even resistance, patiga, of their cetasau, which is of their citta, from that they should reign in the citta.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, I left cetas and citta in Pali because... just to kind of indicate things that are pertaining to citta and that are kind of cittas doing, to put it that way.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because with the word mind, mind this, mind that, mano-mind, my mind, citta-mind, it kind of gets, it gets a bit blurred.
[SPEAKER_00]: And also, same, it's like with the word resistance, patīgā, because, like, if you look at the common translations, they just say aversion.
[SPEAKER_00]: Oh, if there is even aversion in my mind.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, again, it kind of becomes the whole meaning of this very obviously short, like, what, three lines.
[SPEAKER_00]: It becomes flattened in the sense that you could see the clearly, like, the first paragraph says, should there arise desire, or greed, or hate, i.e.
[SPEAKER_00]: aversion, or delusion, or even a patiga.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, it's different than hate.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's different than aversion.
[SPEAKER_00]: But if you just translate it,
[SPEAKER_00]: Like, oh, greed, hate, delusion, or even any aversion, it kind of becomes like a poetic sort of... and it completely loses the depth.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because it's the patīgā of their cetasā, not just, oh, some slight aversion, because somebody didn't put sugar in my coffee or something.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's a bit more phenomenological than that.
[SPEAKER_00]: And that's kind of the point of why, like, sometimes it's good to leave certain things completely untranslated.
[SPEAKER_00]: So it says, basically, so yes, if any of these things are found in the citta, stemming from it, being pushed forward by the citta, from that they should reign in the citta.
[SPEAKER_00]: By thinking this.
[SPEAKER_00]: This path is fearful, with terror, with thorns, with thickets, a wrong path, a bad path, difficult to travel.
[SPEAKER_00]: This path of desire, of greed, of hate, of delusion, that path.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, this path is frequented by ignoble, āsapurisa.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's not the path frequented by the noble, sapurisa.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, it doesn't lead to wisdom, basically.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's not worthy of you.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, it's like a generic stock phrase to describe a type of reflection that you need to be bringing in front of your citta, in front of your mind, sustaining it, reminding it, like relentlessly reminding it of that.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because, again, when the animal wants to go over the fence, you need to remind it why it is dangerous to do so.
[SPEAKER_00]: And if it wants to go over the fence frequently, well, you frequently have to remind it.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's not one and done.
[SPEAKER_00]: And then, it goes to repeat the same.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, one should train the citta from forms cognizable by the eye, sight, sounds, smell, taste, touches, basically, ideas as well.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, when mental
[SPEAKER_00]: When thoughts, mental phenomena, images present themselves, you would see the citta wanting to leap towards them with lust, with greed, with hatred.
[SPEAKER_00]: You have to rein it in.
[SPEAKER_00]: Like, say no and then remind it of the drawbacks, of the dangers of doing so and benefits of not doing so.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, it repeats the same.
[SPEAKER_00]: This path is fearful, with terror, with thorns, with thickets.
[SPEAKER_00]: Thickets, a wrong path, a bad path, difficult to travel.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, frequented by ignoble, not frequented by the noble.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's not worthy.
[SPEAKER_00]: And again, why is it not worthy?
[SPEAKER_00]: Well, anybody who wants to practice the Buddha's teaching,
[SPEAKER_00]: You should be aligning, aspiring towards and working towards alignment with the values presented by the Buddha, because you yourself see the value in those values, so to speak.
[SPEAKER_00]: Like, you see the value in training, you have faith in it, so that you can be free from suffering.
[SPEAKER_00]: You have a genuine, profound desire to be free from dukkha, free from liability, free from attachment, free from any danger.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, it's a real thing.
[SPEAKER_00]: But it's just like, if you forget that, then citta can pressure you back to things you know are an obstacle for what you actually want.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's like that, eh... What is it?
[SPEAKER_00]: Talaputta, yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: I think it was Talaputta.
[SPEAKER_00]: In that, eh... Terra Terrigata, when... when he was talking to his own citta back when he was in the forest.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because... and saying basically, like, oh, before I became a monk, when I was a householder, my own mind was telling me, hey, leave this crowded and dusty life, go forth,
[SPEAKER_00]: Enjoy the freedom of the wilderness, you know, practice for the freedom of suffering.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, he was quite inspired, basically.
[SPEAKER_00]: His own mind was quite inspired to practice.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, then he did it.
[SPEAKER_00]: He went forth, then went to the forest, and now the mind was like, whoa, yeah, you know, we did this, like, now I want something else.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, then he wanted to go back, and then he was saying to the mind, like, hold on, but you were the one that brought me here.
[SPEAKER_00]: Now, you want to go back to that which you yourself said was not worthy and everything else.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, then he's like, no.
[SPEAKER_00]: No, I'm gonna make you sit here now with me, and we're gonna work through this, and you're not going back.
[SPEAKER_00]: And, yeah, he worked through it and became an arahant.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, it says like, oh, suppose because there was a rich crop, the crop guardian is negligent,
[SPEAKER_00]: And a crop-eating ox, having entered that crop, would indulge himself in intoxication and negligence as much as he wants.
[SPEAKER_00]: Even so, because an uninstructed whirling, asutava, putujana, acting without restraint in the six bases of pressure, passa, I translated it as pressure, well, most of you already know that, indulges in intoxication and negligence as much as he wants in the five strands of sensual pleasure.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, it's kind of... even pertains to somebody who say... who's just at the very beginning of the practice, which would be the the asūtava, the uninstructed worldling, who might have started learning some instruction.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, allowing the mind, the citta,
[SPEAKER_00]: To enter the crop, indulge itself in the crop as much as it wants, with intoxication and negligence, towards the sensuality, the five strands of sensual pleasure, equals what the previous paragraph just described.
[SPEAKER_00]: Equals following the ignoble path that takes away from wisdom, that obstructs the wisdom, and does not lead to freedom from suffering.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's kind of pretty self-evident, really.
[SPEAKER_00]: But, it doesn't matter how self-evident it is.
[SPEAKER_00]: When the pressure is there, to act out of the greed, desire and so on, eh... the context is lost.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, as I said, that's why, like, you have to remind yourself of what you actually want, what you actually value, and then rein in the mind.
[SPEAKER_00]: And that, that's the principle of that training, is, like, from asuttava putujana up to the arahantship.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's the part that doesn't change whatsoever.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, then, the next... let me just scroll this up, yeah...
[SPEAKER_00]: So, then, the next paragraph is the opposite.
[SPEAKER_00]: In other words, teach him a lesson.
[SPEAKER_00]: Like, no, you don't go there.
[SPEAKER_00]: Like, we've been through this before.
[SPEAKER_00]: We rationalized many times.
[SPEAKER_00]: Both you and I know that that this is the the ignoble path, the obstruction.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's just there's no more discussion, in other words.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's just like grab you by the nose and pull you back.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, and then even even the sutta describes.
[SPEAKER_00]: And then second time the ox does it.
[SPEAKER_00]: Then the third time.
[SPEAKER_00]: Then the hundred and third time does it.
[SPEAKER_00]: You repeat the same.
[SPEAKER_00]: No, you are not going there.
[SPEAKER_00]: I'm not fueling
[SPEAKER_00]: Neither that attitude, nor that behavior.
[SPEAKER_00]: You can kick and scream as much as you want, like a spoiled brat.
[SPEAKER_00]: If you give in, you convey the wrong message.
[SPEAKER_00]: And by giving in, I mean that.
[SPEAKER_00]: Literally, choose to go down that path.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's not like, oh, giving in doesn't mean having your mind... having your mind have a desire.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's not you giving in.
[SPEAKER_00]: Your mind getting angry, citta getting angry.
[SPEAKER_00]: But you choosing to allow it, to act, you to act on account of it, that is you giving in.
[SPEAKER_00]: So that's why you don't need to, as I said, strangle or kill your mind or not perceive anything to be free from it.
[SPEAKER_00]: You just not be the one, you just not, you must not be the one who would be making the choice of, yeah, okay, go ahead into the crop.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, the problem is not that the animal wants to go back to the crop and eat as much as it wants and so on.
[SPEAKER_00]: The problem is that you keep letting it.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's it.
[SPEAKER_00]: And that's that line of the restraint.
[SPEAKER_00]: Like, you don't need to torment yourself, you don't need to sleep on the bed of nails and stuff like that to just somehow magically cure the mind from desires.
[SPEAKER_00]: Like, no, you just need to be... to recognize that you must not be the one willingly, consciously making the choice that affirms sensuality, greed, aversion, distraction and so on.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's the middle path.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, you recognize that and then the practice will not necessarily be unpleasant.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because, again, like you just... yeah, the mind comes like this, the mind sometimes comes up like that.
[SPEAKER_00]: This is the line I won't cross.
[SPEAKER_00]: Everything else outside of that line is not my problem.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, it's like a lot of burden comes down from you.
[SPEAKER_00]: So then, it compares this bringing back of the ox, compares, the Buddha compares that to a monk taming his cheetah.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, even so, the paragraph says, for a bhikkhu, the cheetah is tamed, well tamed, regarding the six bases of pressure, in other words, the six types of crops.
[SPEAKER_00]: Well, the animal learned its lesson.
[SPEAKER_00]: You're not letting it go there.
[SPEAKER_00]: You bring it back, you present it with perceptions and you're diligent in that regard.
[SPEAKER_00]: You don't go around complaining, feeling sorry for yourself because your mind still wants these things.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because, again, it's like literally complaining that, well, the dog still wants to go and chew the bone.
[SPEAKER_00]: Well, yeah, what a surprise.
[SPEAKER_00]: Still wants to go and chase other animals.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah, what a surprise.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's what the animal does.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's what citta does.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, it's like,
[SPEAKER_00]: No, that's not my problem.
[SPEAKER_00]: My problem is if I'm the one opening the gate and then paying the price for it.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, I'll stop doing that and the annual will come out.
[SPEAKER_00]: How long it takes to come down?
[SPEAKER_00]: Well, we'll just have to see once that happens.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, it says, even so, because when for a bhikkhu the citta is tamed, well-tamed regarding the six bases of pressure, six types of crops, it remains centered within.
[SPEAKER_00]: It settles down, it becomes unified, it enters samādhi.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, when the mind is tamed, when citta is tamed in regard to the six bases of contact, how?
[SPEAKER_00]: Well, the Buddha just described in the same sense how a shepherd would use a stick to prevent the ox from going into the wrong crops.
[SPEAKER_00]: That is how.
[SPEAKER_00]: He can't be any clearer than that.
[SPEAKER_00]: Really, even the simile is not technical.
[SPEAKER_00]: Then, the mind settles down and becomes unified.
[SPEAKER_00]: Then, you enter samādhi.
[SPEAKER_00]: Then, you develop samādhi.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, if there is no samādhi, it's because there is no right training in regard to the crop.
[SPEAKER_00]: There is still that allowing the oxygen to go into the crop as much as you want, despite what you might be telling yourself or what you might be believing.
[SPEAKER_00]: And then it goes into kind of the second half, giving a simile in regarding to the lute and the king.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, suppose because the sound of a lute was never heard before by a king or a royal minister.
[SPEAKER_00]: He might hear a sound of the lute and say, good man, whose sound is this?
[SPEAKER_00]: So enchanting, so desirable, so intoxicating, so infatuating, so captivating.
[SPEAKER_00]: They would say to him, well, this, sir, is the... that which is called the lute, the sound of which is so enchanting and captivating.
[SPEAKER_00]: He would then say, go, man, bring me that lute.
[SPEAKER_00]: They would bring him the lute.
[SPEAKER_00]: And he would say, enough of it, bring me just the sound.
[SPEAKER_00]: Then, they would explain to him that this luta is made of many components, of great components.
[SPEAKER_00]: It speaks, it speaks having dependent on many components, depending on the parchment, the belly, the arm, the bridge, the strings, the plectrum, depending on the appropriate effort of a person.
[SPEAKER_00]: Thus, this luta, sir, is, or sire, is made of many components.
[SPEAKER_00]: It speaks having dependent on many components.
[SPEAKER_00]: Then the man, the king, would choose to split the loot into ten or hundred pieces.
[SPEAKER_00]: Having split it, he would splinter it.
[SPEAKER_00]: Having splintered it, he would burn it with fire and make it into ashes.
[SPEAKER_00]: Having made it into ashes, he would winnow it in a strong wind and let it be carried away by a swift flowing river.
[SPEAKER_00]: He would say, a poor thing indeed is this so-called loot.
[SPEAKER_00]: Whatever a loot may be, herein, the people are excessively negligent and deceived.
[SPEAKER_00]: Meaning, he destroyed the loot, trying to get to the sound, and there was no sound.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, he couldn't find the sound.
[SPEAKER_00]: We'll get to that part when we do the questions later, as to why this is relevant to the first part.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, it says, even so, because Abhikūr investigates form, as far as the designation or destination of form goes, he investigates feeling, he investigates perception, he investigates determinations, he investigates consciousness, yes.
[SPEAKER_00]: As he investigates form, feeling, perception, determination, consciousness, as far as the destination of consciousness goes, whatever there was of I am, of mine, that for him is no more.
[SPEAKER_00]: So...
[SPEAKER_00]: So, yeah, that whole kind of... the second part is just to illustrate, let's say, like an inside view of
[SPEAKER_00]: Of the desire that you're taming through practicing the first part of the sutta, which is bringing the oxen back from the crop.
[SPEAKER_00]: Bringing the oxen back from the crop.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, the few questions that I compiled, they kind of, sort of, try to bridge the theory and the practice between this, in this sutta.
[SPEAKER_00]: was the the question of the the leaking fence, or the not properly closed gate, or whatever similar comparison you want to use.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, in the simile of the ox, the guardian only strikes the ox when it enters the crop.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, you don't go around beating it all the time, if it's not doing anything wrong.
[SPEAKER_00]: What is wrong in this context?
[SPEAKER_00]: Well, the sutta clearly describes it.
[SPEAKER_00]: Sensual desire is wrong, greed is wrong, hatred, anger is wrong, and so on.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, in one's daily life, can you discern your citta as something that's already leaning towards those things?
[SPEAKER_00]: In other words, can you notice when the animal is already inclining or planning to try and sneak through the gate?
[SPEAKER_00]: Or do you only see it when it's right there and you're trying to, like, drag it back from the wrong crop?
[SPEAKER_00]: Because that's the important factor.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's like if you're waiting for the bull to be entering the crop to start paying attention, it's too late.
[SPEAKER_00]: Usually, it's too late.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, you need to start noticing the tendencies of your mind way before it comes into, like, a full-blown
[SPEAKER_00]: Oh, now I just have to be beating it with a stick and pulling it by the nose and it's really hard because it weighs a ton.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, that's like... Obviously, it's like a very important consideration, but it's also something, as I said, it's like you have to...
[SPEAKER_00]: It's gonna have layers to it.
[SPEAKER_00]: In other words, you know, you might think you're noticing the... the... the background state of the animal.
[SPEAKER_00]: Oh, is my mind leaning and so on?
[SPEAKER_00]: But, you can know whether you're, say, correctly or accurately enough doing that noticing, if when the animal is at the doorstep of the crop, are you able to actually pull it back?
[SPEAKER_00]: Are you able to not let it go that way?
[SPEAKER_00]: Or, like, okay, we're just eating in the crop now and then I'll start again later.
[SPEAKER_00]: If that's the case, if that's the case more often than not, means you are not noticing the state of the animal early enough.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, you gotta start... you gotta stop distracting yourself with other seemingly important things and look backwards, peripheral, at the background of your mind, what kind of
[SPEAKER_00]: Sort of, like, moods, inclinations are there, leaning, shaping up.
[SPEAKER_00]: Like, what kind of clouds are coming up the horizon?
[SPEAKER_00]: Way before you are hit by a storm.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because that is the reason why the animal is still able... why you're not able to pull the animal out of the crop, basically.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's just... it's too late.
[SPEAKER_00]: The second question is about the Sutta describing the whole path of following desire or aversion.
[SPEAKER_00]: Either way, desire as sensual desire, aversion as ill will, hatred, acting out.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's all on the same plane, pertains to the world, so to speak.
[SPEAKER_00]: The Sutta describes it as the path which is like a path covered with thorns.
[SPEAKER_00]: Dangerous path where you're just gonna injure yourself.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, that's this... the question is, like, when the... when that patīgā, that, as I said, the natural, the fundamental, the underlying resistance toward your own senses... Well, resistance of citta towards your own senses.
[SPEAKER_00]: Pretty technical.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, whether it's just a neutral patīgā...
[SPEAKER_00]: It's still a resistance, by the way, so it can never be entirely neutral.
[SPEAKER_00]: But what I'm saying, that is, patīgā is not necessarily aversion.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's not necessarily hatred or real will.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's where hatred or ill will finds its basis from.
[SPEAKER_00]: Same.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's in the same sense how a sign of subha, the sign of beautiful agreeable shape, form, sound, doesn't matter.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's not where sensuality is, but it's where sensuality finds its base from.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, whether it's as subtle as that neutral patīgā, that resistance that you just have towards pretty much your own physicality, naturally, because senses are a burden, they offer inertia, that inertia is patīgā.
[SPEAKER_00]: Well, but whether that patīgā becomes your own aversion, that's a secondary thing.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, the question here, it's like, how far can you go back and notice
[SPEAKER_00]: The precursors to your desire or real will, the the clouds, they're coming up the horizon.
[SPEAKER_00]: Or do you need to, like, have them right in front of your face to become aware of them?
[SPEAKER_00]: If so, it's because, most likely, you're probably distracting yourself too much with other things and not investing enough time to contemplate, sit quietly with this and think it, like,
[SPEAKER_00]: You know, invoke it, remember it, recollect it, try to clarify it, and so on.
[SPEAKER_00]: And then see it apply their life, so to speak.
[SPEAKER_00]: Like, okay, so what is the current, the widest possible horizon of my current mood?
[SPEAKER_00]: What is it?
[SPEAKER_00]: Because that whole, like a horizon...
[SPEAKER_00]: I think I remember it was Nyanavira and Nyanamoli discussing it in the early letters.
[SPEAKER_00]: It was like...
[SPEAKER_00]: They were describing relationship, if I remember correctly, between citta and cetanā as like a horizon and things arising from that horizon.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, it's like it sets up the direction and then things arise from there.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, that's why it's... it's like... it's important for that phenomenon to be... to... well...
[SPEAKER_00]: To not be as theoretical for people, but to actually start to relate to it in your own practical, like, experience, day-to-day experience as a whole.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because it is there.
[SPEAKER_00]: All these moods and precursors and wide, kind of, as I said, very, very peripheral leaning and preferences are there and they are leaning you and setting you up for what's to follow out of them.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, the sooner you spot them there, obviously, the less kind of physical effort you will have to apply onto the bull to pull him back.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: So...
[SPEAKER_00]: So, yeah, now the whole simile of the lute.
[SPEAKER_00]: Sister Iveka mentioned in her reply before, it's like a simile compared to a rainbow, which I think is quite a good simile.
[SPEAKER_00]: Like, the king wants the sound of the lute, but ignores the existing, presently, simultaneously existing unity of its parts.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because you can have the strings, you can have the body, you could have the musician, but if you have them separate, not unified in that particular arrangement, you will not have the sound of the lute.
[SPEAKER_00]: And it's the same, exactly the same with the rainbow.
[SPEAKER_00]: Now, does that mean rainbow is not real as such?
[SPEAKER_00]: Does that mean sound of the lute is not real as such?
[SPEAKER_00]: No, not at all.
[SPEAKER_00]: There would be a lazy way out, saying, oh, because you can take it apart, it doesn't exist in some sort of imaginable reality.
[SPEAKER_00]: But that's just basic kind of contradiction in terms.
[SPEAKER_00]: And it's quite an irrational standpoint, which is why mysticism comes out of it.
[SPEAKER_00]: No, it is real as such.
[SPEAKER_00]: Nobody denies that the lute has a pleasant sound.
[SPEAKER_00]: But the sound, it's not found in any of the specific components.
[SPEAKER_00]: Nobody denies that I am factually seeing the rainbow.
[SPEAKER_00]: I mean, I can describe the colors, I can even describe the size.
[SPEAKER_00]: Oh, there's a double one, look.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, it's like, so what?
[SPEAKER_00]: Is that not real?
[SPEAKER_00]: No, it's real.
[SPEAKER_00]: But, obviously, if I look for it where it isn't, it's not going to be there.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, why is this relevant?
[SPEAKER_00]: Well, desire is the same.
[SPEAKER_00]: Ill-will is the same.
[SPEAKER_00]: Pretty much any pressure
[SPEAKER_00]: The citta exerts on you, it's the same nature.
[SPEAKER_00]: See, you see the rainbow, the experience of it, the natural pressure of unenlightened mind is to push you towards it.
[SPEAKER_00]: But towards what?
[SPEAKER_00]: It's there when you are not close or too close to it, so to speak, or when you're not too far.
[SPEAKER_00]: So it's there the way it is there.
[SPEAKER_00]: But the tendency of the mind is to push you forward, to push you for more of it.
[SPEAKER_00]: And you don't know where to look for more of it.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, where do you look?
[SPEAKER_00]: Well, you look among the sense objects.
[SPEAKER_00]: You look among the forms, the feeling, all the other palpable things.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's why, after the Simile of the Loot, the Buddha started describing the aggregates, how when the monk starts looking at the aggregates, he won't find the sense of I am there.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because the sense of I am shares the same nature.
[SPEAKER_00]: But on a more... well...
[SPEAKER_00]: On a more practical level, for somebody, say, who is kind of still working on that training the ox, you could see exactly the same principle revealed in just the essential desire.
[SPEAKER_00]: And I'm pretty sure, like, everybody, with anyone, with some degree of self-awareness, but, say, outside of the context of the Buddhist practice, outside of the suttas,
[SPEAKER_00]: Deep down, has a recognition, because it has happened so many times, you have a desire towards something.
[SPEAKER_00]: You have that pressure towards something perceived, currently, as a kind of dependent on the unified components of your experience, to put it that way, on sights, eyes, desire, this and that.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, it's like, that kind of pressure, it's real as such, to that extent.
[SPEAKER_00]: But then, what would people naturally do?
[SPEAKER_00]: Well, then, they would go for more of the sights, more of this.
[SPEAKER_00]: But they themselves would then experience that, oh, well, this was a bit of a letdown.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because you don't find it there.
[SPEAKER_00]: You don't find those things there.
[SPEAKER_00]: Same with the food.
[SPEAKER_00]: Like, it's that, pretty much, joy of anticipation is where your happiness, what your happiness is bound with.
[SPEAKER_00]: Once you start eating or consuming or doing this, you went too far.
[SPEAKER_00]: And you just find yourself, okay, desire is gone, because the phenomenon of rainbow is gone, because I went too far.
[SPEAKER_00]: The angle changed, there are no more water droplets there or whatever.
[SPEAKER_00]: And that's why each time, it sets you up from the beginning, so to speak, to fail in exactly the same way.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because you're looking for it where it can't be found.
[SPEAKER_00]: And now, the same principle of just the basic core central desire that always sets you towards sense objects.
[SPEAKER_00]: But, as I was saying that a long time ago in those talks from Sri Lanka, it's like... A mere thought of seeing or touching or tasting something already produces, like,
[SPEAKER_00]: Excitement, dissipation, desire, pressure, even more.
[SPEAKER_00]: But it's like... but hold on.
[SPEAKER_00]: If, through a common asutava-putujana belief, pleasure is in touching, tasting, seeing, smelling, listening, and so on, how can you already experience the pleasure way before you are in contact with those things?
[SPEAKER_00]: Way before you even went and kind of sought it, and found it, and looked at it, and ate it, and so on.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yet, you're experiencing the same.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, it's like, if it's truly in those things, you could only experience it when you are actively in contact with them.
[SPEAKER_00]: But that's the point.
[SPEAKER_00]: It was never in those things.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, the more you are ignoring the whole necessity of restraint, necessity of training in virtue, necessity of withdrawing the ox,
[SPEAKER_00]: The more you are reinforcing the belief that, as I said, even a sutta puthujjana, when he's honest with himself, knows that, yeah, things are not really satisfying at the end of the day.
[SPEAKER_00]: Like, doesn't matter how much...
[SPEAKER_00]: But, I forget about that, and then I continue to kind of distract myself with the thrill of the chase.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, it's like chasing the the rainbows while I know I can't find them.
[SPEAKER_00]: But, anyway, I ignore that part.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because, again, deactivation is what gives me joy.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, that's why this simile is relevant.
[SPEAKER_00]: Relevant to the whole restraint and everything.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, it's like in the in the beginning, yes, you have to just whack the bull and pull it back and not let it go there.
[SPEAKER_00]: But, eventually, you have to start seeing through the whole pattern.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's like, hold on.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yes, there is pressure.
[SPEAKER_00]: But, how many times, like even before the restraint and after restraint, I know it's not in those things.
[SPEAKER_00]: Now, my citta needs to know that.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, that's why these perceptions of the danger and so on.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, they're the same knowledge.
[SPEAKER_00]: The obviousness of it will sink to the mind, down to the mind.
[SPEAKER_00]: And when it does so, you don't have to be pulling the oxen back.
[SPEAKER_00]: It won't go there, because there is nothing there to find from the beginning.
[SPEAKER_00]: What you thought it was getting from those things, it wasn't there.
[SPEAKER_00]: And that was the sole problem.
[SPEAKER_00]: There was a sole deception of sensuality and stuff, all the similes that we talked about.
[SPEAKER_00]: Like, if it were not a deception, it would not have been unwholesome.
[SPEAKER_00]: And it's actually another sutta, isn't it?
[SPEAKER_00]: Where the Buddha says, māra, oh, sorry, hunter does not set up a trap for the welfare of the animal.
[SPEAKER_00]: It just cannot be done for that purpose.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, a hunter does not set up a trap, because he sets up the trap to get the animal, to get the meat, to hunt you down.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, it's like, you can't go around, you can't see a hunter.
[SPEAKER_00]: But imagine yourself entering a forest and you see something that
[SPEAKER_00]: Really looks like a trap.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's like, hmm, this looks like it's trying to get me to go there for whatever reason.
[SPEAKER_00]: A man with, like, normal rational mind and a normal, as I said, common sense wisdom, would, as such a man, choose to go there, or was like, no?
[SPEAKER_00]: No, I probably wouldn't.
[SPEAKER_00]: Like, why would I?
[SPEAKER_00]: It's like, the way... like, if something needs to be set up to get you there first, it's something you naturally wouldn't trust.
[SPEAKER_00]: And it's exactly how sensuality is set up.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's set up to get you there first, and then the person's like, but hold on.
[SPEAKER_00]: If I'm already feeling the pressure before I even got there, means that's already a setup that has nothing to do with things I'm trying to get to.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, why would I go there?
[SPEAKER_00]: It can't be for my welfare.
[SPEAKER_00]: If somebody set this up in this manner, it cannot be for my welfare, because it's deceitful.
[SPEAKER_00]: And that's one of the dangers of sensuality.
[SPEAKER_00]: All the other implications that you trapped yourself in.
[SPEAKER_00]: As the Sutta says, the ox eventually stops entering the crop, because it... well, it learned from the stick.
[SPEAKER_00]: It learned from your relentless recollection of the right perception, sustaining the context at the right time,
[SPEAKER_00]: As I said, you don't have to go around reciting the danger of sensuality 24-7 as some sort of mantra.
[SPEAKER_00]: No.
[SPEAKER_00]: But when you recognize that you are being pressured towards choosing sensuality or ill-will, that's when you bring up those contexts.
[SPEAKER_00]: No exception.
[SPEAKER_00]: No slacking.
[SPEAKER_00]: If the mind doesn't come up with it, great.
[SPEAKER_00]: Put your feet up and relax.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, the question here was like, do you... like, do you do these such reflections?
[SPEAKER_00]: Do you... do you remember yourself?
[SPEAKER_00]: Like,
[SPEAKER_00]: Times in the past, when you allowed sensuality, when you acted out of ill-will and so on, well, was it pleasant?
[SPEAKER_00]: Was it beneficial?
[SPEAKER_00]: Who was the main benefactor of it?
[SPEAKER_00]: You or the wild animal?
[SPEAKER_00]: They get you to do it.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's like...
[SPEAKER_00]: So, recognizing those implicitly kind of unpleasant ways,
[SPEAKER_00]: Do you recollect that as well, the emotional side of those things, to make it, as I said, more pertinent of a reflection, rather than just theoretically, as I said, recite through danger.
[SPEAKER_00]: Actually, feel the danger, in other words.
[SPEAKER_00]: Feel the drawbacks.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, make the connection.
[SPEAKER_00]: Make the connection between the drawbacks of things that followed.
[SPEAKER_00]: See, you could say like, oh, I don't see a connection between, like, giving sensuality and then something that's happening.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's like, yeah, but something else that can happen.
[SPEAKER_00]: Unfavorable.
[SPEAKER_00]: That can happen.
[SPEAKER_00]: And you know your mind will kick and scream and suffer and try and bite you as a result and you would suffer.
[SPEAKER_00]: Well, that is because that mind is untrained.
[SPEAKER_00]: Why is that mind untrained?
[SPEAKER_00]: Well, because you've been allowing it into sensuality and into ill-will carelessly.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, there is a connection.
[SPEAKER_00]: You just need to not forget it, and when you forget it, you need to remember it, you need to clarify it and protect it, so that next time there's sensuality, you see all the other collateral damage implied in it, so to speak.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, yeah, and then, in the end, the presence of the I am, of I am, that was, as I said, if you follow the same principle,
[SPEAKER_00]: Of the rainbow existing real as such, or the sound of the lute being real as such, yet dependent on things that are not it, that are defining it.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's the same with the presence of I am.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, the presence of I am is real as such.
[SPEAKER_00]: Your sense of whoever you are is real as such.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's not an illusion.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's not an anatta.
[SPEAKER_00]: Nothing is real.
[SPEAKER_00]: Nothing is mine.
[SPEAKER_00]: No.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's real as such.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's just a mistaken identity.
[SPEAKER_00]: You think of it more than it actually is, to put it that way.
[SPEAKER_00]: You think rainbow is over there, you know, 350 meters away, in those molecules, and if I go there and get it, I'll find it, I'll have it.
[SPEAKER_00]: King thought sound of the lute was in the strings, so he started dissecting it and taking it apart.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, it's like, that's why, again, you can't dissect your own aggregates.
[SPEAKER_00]: I mean, you can try,
[SPEAKER_00]: But the result would be absolutely destroyed loot and now without any capacity for the sound or understanding of the relationship between the two.
[SPEAKER_00]: So that when the Buddha says you examine the form and stuff, you examine the nature of the form as that which kind of enables the sense of I am to depend on it.
[SPEAKER_00]: And you just... you go... you don't need to go further than that.
[SPEAKER_00]: You don't need to start tormenting, torturing, destroying... torturing, destroying your form, your feelings and so on, your consciousness.
[SPEAKER_00]: I mean, I don't know how you would do that, but people might try, in order to prove yourself that... that a sense of I am is not yours.
[SPEAKER_00]: No, you just need to basically stop thinking of yourself as independent of form, feeling, perception, determination and consciousness.
[SPEAKER_00]: Literally, that's it.
[SPEAKER_00]: Stop regarding yourself as the owner.
[SPEAKER_00]: Contemplate the impermanence to undermine the safety, the emotional safety of the sense of ownership.
[SPEAKER_00]: Not just to, like, as I said, fall into a theoretical view that everything is constantly changing, therefore nothing is really mine, therefore everything is anatta, therefore the Buddha was right.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's like, no, no, no.
[SPEAKER_00]: If you truly develop anatta, well, you'll be free from suffering.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, the contemplation, the dissections, the analysis that the suttas describe, it's not mindless scientific scholarly analysis of random components, like how Abhidhamma or commentaries do it.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's the actual contemplation of the live situation being undermined by something else that's there.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, it's like, oh, I'm hearing the sound of the lute.
[SPEAKER_00]: But I'm not forgetting that it depends on these quite irrelevant, emotionally insignificant or even disgusting parts in and of themselves.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's why, you know, the contemplation of the body and the dangers and so on that other suttas talk about.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's to just lose the desire towards the sound of the lute.
[SPEAKER_00]: Lose the enchantment and the ridiculous idea of chasing the rainbow.
[SPEAKER_00]: Or, become un-intoxicated with your own sense of I am, with your own self-view, sense of I am, conceit and everything else, by undermining it rightly, through recognition of things that do actually determine it, that is inseparable from and depends on.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, that's it.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's the sole purpose of this.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, what is the difference between aversion and patiga?
[SPEAKER_00]: They're all talks.
[SPEAKER_00]: They talk about it more, so I don't want to be going into it.
[SPEAKER_00]: But, I think I already covered it, didn't I?
[SPEAKER_00]: So, think of the resistance basically just as
[SPEAKER_00]: Say there is... you're feeling neutral.
[SPEAKER_00]: Say you're feeling neutral.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, it's like nothing... nothing like bothering you or overtly pressuring you.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, there's no aversion, there's no desire, currently at least.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, you're just sitting.
[SPEAKER_00]: As I said, there is a natural inertia of your existence as a whole.
[SPEAKER_00]: There is a natural weight, you know, the body, the blob that you have to carry, the situation,
[SPEAKER_00]: The heat, the cold, just all the little things are felt through a degree of their own, like, resistance, a degree of that, literally, like, in physics, inertia.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's it.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's a good word.
[SPEAKER_00]: And, again, I think Jnanaviri and Molly were talking about translating rūpa as inertia, as that which offers inertia.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's how you know it's there.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, that's the natural patīgā.
[SPEAKER_00]: When I say patīgā, that in and of itself, it's a bit, as I said, weighty.
[SPEAKER_00]: So to speak.
[SPEAKER_00]: It has some weight on.
[SPEAKER_00]: When that's not seen through, that is the basis.
[SPEAKER_00]: Well, it's kind of the basis for even centrality, when you think about it.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's certainly basis for aversion, but it's base for centrality as well, because it's... if it's not seen through, you will be discontent with it.
[SPEAKER_00]: And discontent, as one of the Mahārāja's daughters, goes hand in hand with sensuality.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because when you are discontent, you will then be seeking, well, the only means of escape from that that you know, which is sensual pleasures, which is falling back into the belief that, if I follow the rainbow, I'll get to the source, the core, the substance, the center of it.
[SPEAKER_00]: And then you just, as I said, deceive yourself with that repetitive ride.
[SPEAKER_00]: But, yeah, that patiga is the base for it.
[SPEAKER_00]: And that's actually that sutta... Well, I can't remember the sutta.
[SPEAKER_00]: I don't remember the numbers anymore, but I do remember it was the... Arhita, yeah, when he said... when the Buddha asked, like, oh, who does the mindfulness of breathing here?
[SPEAKER_00]: And how you do it?
[SPEAKER_00]: And Narita said, I'm doing it.
[SPEAKER_00]: Says, how?
[SPEAKER_00]: I was like, well, mindfully I breathe in, mindfully I breathe out.
[SPEAKER_00]: I know breath is there, or something like that.
[SPEAKER_00]: And he said, having abandoned desire for sense pleasures of the past, having abandoned desire for the sense pleasures of the future,
[SPEAKER_00]: And the present, obviously, I'm abiding now free from internal patiga.
[SPEAKER_00]: Like, not, obviously, seeing through the internal patiga, there is no more desire for any forms of pleasure, even the ones that I used to experience.
[SPEAKER_00]: And the Buddha said, yep, that is one way of doing ānāpānasati, but it's not complete.
[SPEAKER_00]: And then went, well, the sutta goes into the stock phrase of, like, repeating the other, like, you know, I will breathe in like this, I will breathe in like that.
[SPEAKER_00]: Kind of showing that there are probably, there will be more nuances
[SPEAKER_00]: But I don't think that the suttas necessarily have preserved those nuances of descriptions, which is obviously a shame, but nothing we can do about it.
[SPEAKER_00]: But pointing out that, okay, yeah, great, now do it even more and kind of completely uproot the sense of I am.
[SPEAKER_00]: That would be the result of fulfilling the ānāpānasati done rightly, the right recollection.
[SPEAKER_00]: But, as Arita explained, it was like, the way he was describing it, you could see like, aha, seeing through patīgā internally, being free from it, by seeing through it, he has no desire towards sensual pleasures.
[SPEAKER_00]: Which is exactly how it works.
[SPEAKER_00]: If your own presence, neutral presence of your own senses, the weight, the inertia, is not bothersome to the citta, let alone you, your own animal does not mind them.
[SPEAKER_00]: Well, you would feel fairly light.
[SPEAKER_00]: Fairly unburdened.
[SPEAKER_00]: Fairly freed.
[SPEAKER_00]: And yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: And that would be physically felt.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's kind of the funny irony of it.
[SPEAKER_00]: But again, you won't be able to deal with that patiga if you're still having... acting out of sensuality, sexuality, coarse sensuality, ill will and so on.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's like this... this... this is way too buried by those acts that are obviously rooted in it.
[SPEAKER_00]: And then the... the second question was
[SPEAKER_00]: The way to explain to the citta that aversion or sensuality is like a thorn is... well, one of the ways is as I suppose to contemplate the benefit of the peaceful neutral feeling.
[SPEAKER_00]: Well, yes, if you contemplate the danger of following those pressures first.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, how to do this practically?
[SPEAKER_00]: Well, that's how you do it practically.
[SPEAKER_00]: Like, if practically contemplating benefits of the neutral feeling are not quite doing it for the citta, it's not listening to you, well, then you have to practically contemplate the dangers of it.
[SPEAKER_00]: Something a bit a bit heavier.
[SPEAKER_00]: And when that kind of scares it back, then you show it what's actually... See?
[SPEAKER_00]: When you don't go there, this is what you get.
[SPEAKER_00]: And this is actually beneficial.
[SPEAKER_00]: But if you're trying to show to a raging animal that staying calm is peaceful, it's not going to see it.
[SPEAKER_00]: So you can't really force the contemplation of the neutral feeling.
[SPEAKER_00]: It needs to be... the peace of it needs to be discerned and recognized on account of not following
[SPEAKER_00]: The pleasure... the pressure that comes out of the... the craving towards more pleasure, the craving to... to get rid of the aversion and pain and so on, and not acting out of those things.
[SPEAKER_00]: So that... that... that is the only practical method that you can really do.
[SPEAKER_00]: It seems... it seems to me that when I do allow the cow to eat from the crop that isn't supposed to, the line between me and the cow is blurred.
[SPEAKER_00]: Is that because appropriation arises with allowing which increases the sense of I am?
[SPEAKER_00]: Well, yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: But, you see, the answer is really not relevant.
[SPEAKER_00]: In a sense, it doesn't matter why it happens.
[SPEAKER_00]: You know exactly why it happens.
[SPEAKER_00]: It happened because the choice you made allowed it to go there.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, stop doing that.
[SPEAKER_00]: You don't have to worry about appropriation and how it comes and why it works and how it works and so on.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, it happens because, well, you lost perspective.
[SPEAKER_00]: The shepherd that was supposed to keep the bull back, didn't, and then lost perspective.
[SPEAKER_00]: And so, what do you do on account of it?
[SPEAKER_00]: It's like, do you wake up?
[SPEAKER_00]: Acknowledge it.
[SPEAKER_00]: Acknowledge the implications of it, the weight of the mistake, in order to help you to, you know, not fall back to it, into it, so easily as before.
[SPEAKER_00]: Or does the shepherd then pretend, okay, well, let's pretend this never happened, won't happen again, next time I'll make a harder determination, and magically believe, and concentrate harder, and go on a longer retreat, and hopefully mind won't go there.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's like, no.
[SPEAKER_00]: The mind doesn't understand any of your token gestures, any of your observances, determinations and things that you magically are kind of trying to... hoping they will transfer the right perceptions down to the animal and they will just stop wanting those things.
[SPEAKER_00]: No, it's like the sutta is very clear.
[SPEAKER_00]: You know what the crop is,
[SPEAKER_00]: If you don't know, well, you learn what a crop is, you learn where the outlines of it are.
[SPEAKER_00]: You cannot not be aware of the choice, as I said, and that's a good thing, because if the problem were truly the fact that animal can still have a desire or real will, well, arahantyu would never be possible, because you have no say in that.
[SPEAKER_00]: And, again, that's what contemporarily, generally, people would think.
[SPEAKER_00]: If I try hard enough, determine hard enough, concentrate hard enough, these things will just disappear.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because they were always the problem.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's like, no.
[SPEAKER_00]: The animal pressuring you to go, well, the animal trying to go to the crop,
[SPEAKER_00]: That's just what animal does.
[SPEAKER_00]: You recognizing that and tolerating it, that's the doorway, that's the problem, that's the crossroad, that's a mistake.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's the obstruction.
[SPEAKER_00]: And that's why arahant should be as possible.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because you stop doing it, you stop fueling it, you stop reinforcing it through the, as I said, ignorant choice, animal will calm down.
[SPEAKER_00]: I mean, countless suttas describe that.
[SPEAKER_00]: Through training in virtue, you develop samādhi.
[SPEAKER_00]: You develop internal, actual peace.
[SPEAKER_00]: Effortless peace.
[SPEAKER_00]: Not peace dependent on the circumstances and right retreat conditions or right inspiration or something.
[SPEAKER_00]: No.
[SPEAKER_00]: Peace on account of the animal not wanting those crops anymore.
[SPEAKER_00]: Genuine safety.
[SPEAKER_00]: The simile of the, you know, the relay chariots as well.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's always what comes to mind.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's like, it will... a purification of virtue, i.e.
[SPEAKER_00]: training the oxen, leads to the purification of the mind, leads to samādhi, which then leads to the purification of the views.
[SPEAKER_00]: And that's exactly what I've said, like the questioning now, why does appropriation happen?
[SPEAKER_00]: It's like questioning the views while the crop, you know, is still not guarded.
[SPEAKER_00]: But if you guard the crop, animal actually calms down, you see through that, then you will understand appropriation.
[SPEAKER_00]: The views will be purified on account of that.
[SPEAKER_00]: And same works with the right view.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's not a... it's not a... it's not a magic bullet that just hits you out of nowhere.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's like, you start taming, as the Sutta says.
[SPEAKER_00]: A Sutta Upatīcchana does this because he's a Suttava.
[SPEAKER_00]: If somebody is Suttava and learns, he'll stop doing.
[SPEAKER_00]: He stops allowing the oxen to go into sensuality, to act out of ill will.
[SPEAKER_00]: He'll start training it, because he learned.
[SPEAKER_00]: He starts training it, because he learned the oxen will come down.
[SPEAKER_00]: He'll get to see it and then he get to recognize that this sense of I am is dependent on the existing components of this simultaneously existing experience as a whole, or aggregates, whatever you want to describe it.
[SPEAKER_00]: And he will be unable to now hold on to it as the center of experience, as mine, or find safety in it.
[SPEAKER_00]: He will be free from ātavāda.
[SPEAKER_00]: Follows the same principle, he'll be free from the sense of I am.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's it.
[SPEAKER_00]: But, again, those connections, those perceptions, need to be made through diligent effort by you.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because... Well, probably not any of you, but I think generally, like a wider audience, you can't really blame people for it, but, like, when you hear this, I think many people would just then, aha, okay, so I'll just keep the precepts.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because, obviously, listen, I listened to this talk for two hours, and clearly precepts are very important.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, I'll just keep the precepts.
[SPEAKER_00]: With implicit belief that now everything will fall into place, because I adopted the new set of external observances.
[SPEAKER_00]: But internally, a person remains still not making connections, not drawing right perceptions, not drawing right associations, not showing right things to the animal when it pressures you.
[SPEAKER_00]: And just, okay, no, no, no.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's like, well, you do have a basis.
[SPEAKER_00]: You did get the first chariot of virtue, but you're not really moving it.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, you're not getting any closer to the actual samādhi, because you're doing it blindly.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, you need to learn about the virtue, about the precepts, so that you can understand the principles behind that training.
[SPEAKER_00]: And the principles behind that training is, obviously, what we spoke so many times in so many other talks.
[SPEAKER_00]: Watching for your intentions, not just, well, the rule says this, I don't do it, and I don't think about it.
[SPEAKER_00]: But what if there is no rule?
[SPEAKER_00]: I mean, there were no rules in the beginning.
[SPEAKER_00]: Literally.
[SPEAKER_00]: Imagine that.
[SPEAKER_00]: The Buddha just told the dhamma and everybody who heard it, who understood it, knew what to do.
[SPEAKER_00]: Does that mean killing was allowed?
[SPEAKER_00]: Sexual intercourse was allowed?
[SPEAKER_00]: Lying was allowed?
[SPEAKER_00]: Well, it wasn't stated that it wasn't allowed.
[SPEAKER_00]: How did they know?
[SPEAKER_00]: So, ask yourself, do I know why those things that, well, later were defined as not allowed?
[SPEAKER_00]: In other words, do I know why those things are an obstacle?
[SPEAKER_00]: Or am I just keeping the precepts because, well, I was told to do so, and I have faith in that, I find it inspiring.
[SPEAKER_00]: But, no, no, no.
[SPEAKER_00]: Do I know for myself the principle?
[SPEAKER_00]: Why sexuality is an obstruction to seeing the dhamma, fulfilling the dhamma?
[SPEAKER_00]: Why acting out of ill will is an obstruction to seeing the dhamma, to fulfilling the dhamma?
[SPEAKER_00]: Why, as I said, the wrong speech, gossip, lying, comfort, beautification, why are those things actual obstacle towards fulfilling the dhamma?
[SPEAKER_00]: Because if you don't know, well, that's your priority, really.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's why your virtue is not leading to samādhi, which is not leading to the right view.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because you stopped the chariot.
[SPEAKER_00]: You took it for granted.
[SPEAKER_00]: You thought getting the chariot of virtue is all I need.
[SPEAKER_00]: I got the car.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's right there, in my driveway.
[SPEAKER_00]: But I'm not going with it in the right direction, basically.
[SPEAKER_00]: Bhante, you often say that while appropriation goes away, the sense of self remains.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's not just mine anymore.
[SPEAKER_00]: If I, my, and I am all go away, what, in the Sutta terms, is the thing remaining that feels like the sense of self?
[SPEAKER_00]: So, yeah, see, the problem with this question is that it assumes Puthujjana's point of view and Arahant's point of view at the same time and expects an answer that can satisfy both.
[SPEAKER_00]: And, if I give you an answer that can satisfy both, that won't be the dhamma, because it's not opanaiko.
[SPEAKER_00]: It won't be leading onwards towards the practice.
[SPEAKER_00]: It will be an irrelevant theoretical information that might be correct on the paper, but it completely kills the practice, because it led you to believe that now you know what that is, while you don't.
[SPEAKER_00]: Putujana cannot know what an arahant is, unless he's on the way of becoming one.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, what remains is what you will see if you follow what the Sutta says.
[SPEAKER_00]: When I speak about the sense of self remains, I speak about it practically for those that still have sense of self, because usually that is my audience.
[SPEAKER_00]: Those that don't, they don't need to listen to me.
[SPEAKER_00]: And it's more beneficial, practically, to not fall into the view
[SPEAKER_00]: Oh, yeah, the modern science has proven nothing.
[SPEAKER_00]: Everything is constantly changing.
[SPEAKER_00]: Therefore, everything is anatta.
[SPEAKER_00]: The Buddha was right and so on.
[SPEAKER_00]: Myself is not real.
[SPEAKER_00]: It is real.
[SPEAKER_00]: The rainbow is real.
[SPEAKER_00]: The sound of the lute is real.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, when you say it's not mine, do you regard it as not real?
[SPEAKER_00]: Or do you regard it as real, just not mine?
[SPEAKER_00]: There's a huge difference there.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because more often than not, it's like, oh, not mine, not real.
[SPEAKER_00]: Dismissed.
[SPEAKER_00]: But, if you're dismissing it, basically, you're ignoring the problem.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, I say, no, it is yours.
[SPEAKER_00]: First, acknowledge that it is yours, so that you can see the thing that is yours.
[SPEAKER_00]: See it for what it is.
[SPEAKER_00]: The ambiguous rainbow that's not material.
[SPEAKER_00]: I can't find it in anything more palpable.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's that tendency to find more palpable things.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's pretty much why every puthujjana's effort will fall onto one wrong view or the other.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, learning to see the rainbow, learning to hear the sound of the lute correctly, means undoing that gratuitous dependence on palpability being the measure of realness.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because for as long as that is the state of one's mind, your own feelings won't be regarded as real.
[SPEAKER_00]: Your own thoughts won't be regarded as real.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, it is real.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's yours.
[SPEAKER_00]: Take it up.
[SPEAKER_00]: And then, oh, hold on, this, which is mine, does not quite obey my will.
[SPEAKER_00]: Oh, so, it is real.
[SPEAKER_00]: It just showed me that it has its own inertia.
[SPEAKER_00]: It depends on things that are completely not in my control, equally real.
[SPEAKER_00]: I can say it's mine, but is it really mine?
[SPEAKER_00]: It becomes obvious to you that it's not mine.
[SPEAKER_00]: That it cannot be yours, even if you want it to.
[SPEAKER_00]: And that's all.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's anatta.
[SPEAKER_00]: You don't need to go further than that.
[SPEAKER_00]: Obviously, you need to sustain this, protect it and develop it in that sense.
[SPEAKER_00]: But you don't need more answers and permutations and so on.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because
[SPEAKER_00]: Your sense of self, whatever it is, well, first, for most people, it's not even seen.
[SPEAKER_00]: You need to see it real as such.
[SPEAKER_00]: You need to see the rainbow real as such.
[SPEAKER_00]: You need to see the sound of the lute real as such, neither here nor there.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's kind of the point, isn't it?
[SPEAKER_00]: Like, wherever you look for the sound of the lute, it won't be there.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yet, it's there.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's there when all these there's are there, but it's not in any individual one of them.
[SPEAKER_00]: Same with the rainbow.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's neither here nor there.
[SPEAKER_00]: Sense of I am, sense of self, even your own atavāda, as coarse as it can be, it's neither here nor there.
[SPEAKER_00]: But it is real as such.
[SPEAKER_00]: So stop seeking it on the level of palpability and recognize it real as such as that which is neither here nor there.
[SPEAKER_00]: How do I know?
[SPEAKER_00]: Well, ask yourself a question.
[SPEAKER_00]: Do I have a sense of I am?
[SPEAKER_00]: Do I have a sense of whatever, whoever, whoever I am?
[SPEAKER_00]: Say your name.
[SPEAKER_00]: You do have a sense.
[SPEAKER_00]: When you look for where that sense is, you're not gonna find it.
[SPEAKER_00]: And, as I said, Asutava Putujana's default kind of direction that he will fall into is, ah, therefore it's not real.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because the mind does... well, he himself does not see any... any phenomenological nuances in between.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, if I can't see it, smell it, taste it, touch it, it's not real.
[SPEAKER_00]: And, you know, people would live their whole life like that, thinking their own thoughts are not really real.
[SPEAKER_00]: Their own intentions that make them smell, taste, hear and touch are not real.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, that's like what you need to... what needs to be recognized.
[SPEAKER_00]: And that's... that's what I mean, like the question is kind of assumes the validity of the position that pertains to the beginning and the end of the internal path.
[SPEAKER_00]: And providing an answer to that will not be the dhamma.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because you satisfy both seemingly, but in reality you can't do that.
[SPEAKER_00]: You are either on one side or you're trailing towards the other side.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, what is left there?
[SPEAKER_00]: Well, find out by traveling there yourself.
[SPEAKER_00]: And you travel there yourself by not denying what you have now.
[SPEAKER_00]: By learning how not to own it through undermining its ownership, well, through undermining your ownership of it, and certainly not through denying it or dismissing it.
[SPEAKER_00]: You often emphasize not practicing a subha as a way to get rid of the pressure.
[SPEAKER_00]: In terms of the simile, could we say it's important to pin down the ox, endure the pressure before the beating perception of a subha?
[SPEAKER_00]: Before... yes, well... well, depends how you... what you mean.
[SPEAKER_00]: Like, if in your example, pinning the ox is enduring the pressure, and beating is the perception of a subha, then, yeah, sure.
[SPEAKER_00]: But for somebody, pinning down the ox might be the subha, and beating it is the enduring.
[SPEAKER_00]: I don't know.
[SPEAKER_00]: The point is, yeah, like, if, say, you see the clouds coming up from the horizon, before the pressure is fully developed, then, yeah, you should definitely do a subha.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's where the subha is done.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's where it can pertain to the mind rightly.
[SPEAKER_00]: But if you are now amidst of trying to hold back the bull,
[SPEAKER_00]: And failing, the bull is too strong, and you want the whole thing just to end, and you're doing a subha.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah, that's the general subha.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's how people do it.
[SPEAKER_00]: State of mind came up.
[SPEAKER_00]: I must get rid of it, because I cannot contain it.
[SPEAKER_00]: And why I cannot contain it?
[SPEAKER_00]: Well, I already said that.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because I haven't looked at the horizon at all.
[SPEAKER_00]: I haven't paid attention to it.
[SPEAKER_00]: I haven't discerned its inclinations, preferences growing.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, yeah, now it's too late.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, that's something like people do a subha to get rid of the mind with their mind states.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because they don't see a difference.